2004年1月24日 机遇号火星车着陆火星
On the 24th of January 2004, the Opportunity rover touched down on the surface of Mars.
机遇号火星车是探寻火星存在水的证据的两辆火星车之一
Opportunity was one of two rovers tasked with finding ancient evidence of water on the Martian surface.
在火星崎岖的地表行驶45公里后 它的确找到了水存在的痕迹
After travelling 45km over the incredible Martian landscape, it did exactly that.
尽管它的设计寿命只有90天
Despite a life expectancy of just 90 days,
但它却在火星上足足苟了14年！
Opportunity ended up working on Mars for an incredible 14 years
最终在2018年遭遇特大沙尘暴后失联
before succumbing to an enormous dust storm in 2018.
虽然机遇号已经寿终正寝
Although Opportunity's time has come to an end,
它带来的科学发现却在NASA的好奇号火星车上延续了下来
its incredible scientific discoveries live on in NASA's 'Curiosity' rover.
在六个月的太空飞行后
After a six-month journey through space,
好奇号最终在2012年8月6日抵达火星
Curiosity finally made Mars its home when it touched down on the 6th of August 2012.
载有大量先进设备的它
Armed with an array of advanced tools,
决心找出有关火星气候变化与地质过程的新发现
Curiosity looked to make new discoveries about the Martian climate
and the geological processes that shaped Mars over its lifetime.
抵达火星后
Since arriving on Mars,
好奇号主要把重点放在了科学家们好奇已久的盖尔环形山
Curiosity's main focus has been on Gale crater,
which had been an area of high interest for scientists.
而很快 好奇号就发现了环形山中曾经存在水的强有力的证据
Almost right away, Curiosity found strong evidence that this crater was once filled with water.
曾经存在液态水的河流会携带泥沙和砾石流进环形山中
In the past, rivers of liquid water would have flown into the crater carrying sand, silt and gravel along with it.
随着时间的推移 它们会逐渐积累 留下一层层的岩石 像截图一样等待好奇号发现
Over time,
these layers would build up and compress into rock - leaving a snapshot in time for Curiosity to discover.
为了进一步研究这些古老的构造
In order to further examine these ancient formations,
好奇号钻进了湖床 发现了几种类型的有机化合物
Curiosity drilled into the lake bed and discovered several types of organic compounds.
这些化合物中含有碳元素
These are chemical compounds that contain carbon,
而碳元素正是地球上的生命最常见的元素
one of the most common elements found in life on Earth.
虽然太阳系中有很多碳元素并不是来自于生命
Although there is a lot of carbon in our solar system that doesn't originate from life,
但这仍然是个好消息 可能暗示火星几十亿年前存在过微生物生命
this was a good sign that microbial life could have existed on Mars billions of years ago.
好奇号目前仍在盖尔环形山内
Curiosity continues to travel around Gale crater,
探寻值得观测的地层 分析岩石样本
discovering interesting formations and analyzing rock samples.
目前 好奇号已经在火星行驶了22公里
So far, Curiosity has travelled 22km across the Martian surface -
但并不是一帆风顺
but it hasn't all been smooth sailing.
过去七年中
Over the last 7 years,
火星崎岖的地表已经给好奇号的轮子带来了严重的磨损
the rough Martian terrain has caused a significant amount of damage to Curiosity's wheels.
而这只是好奇号在火星上遇到的无数麻烦之一
This is just one of the many problems that threaten Curiosity on the Martian surface.
为了减缓轮子的损耗
In order to reduce tyre wear,
控制火星车的工程师为它重新规划了路线
the engineers that control the rover have started to re-route Curiosity on its journey,
以避开崎岖路段
to avoid the harshest of terrain.
好奇号也在时刻用深空通信网络与地球保持密切联系
Curiosity remains in close communication with Earth via the Deep Space Network,
关于深空通信网络 av45001759
该网络由分布在地球上的三组天线阵列组成
which consists of antenna complexes at three locations around the world.
好奇号使用一个可调高增益天线直接指向地球
The rover uses a steerable high-gain antenna which can be pointed directly towards Earth.
而和地球直接通信的数据率较低
The data rates when talking directly to Earth are slow,
所以好奇号通常是先将数据发给火星勘测轨道器(MRO)
so Curiosity often sends its data through the Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter.
MRO每天会在好奇号头顶飞过8分钟
This orbiter passes over the rover for around 8 minutes each day.
在如此短的时间内
In that short period of time,
好奇号可以将大概30MB的数据传给MRO
Curiosity can send around 30 megabytes of data up to the orbiter
之后转发给地球
which can then pass it onto Earth.
如果让好奇号传同样的数据直送地球 则要花费20小时
If Curiosity was to send the same amount of data directly to Earth, it would take 20 hours.
与地球直接通信还会消耗航天器的大量电池电量
Communicating directly with Earth also uses a lot of power from the spacecrafts batteries,
所以数据传送每天只能进行几小时
so sending information can only be done for a few hours per day.
好奇号的电力来自于放射性同位素热电机(RTG)
Curiosity is powered by a radioactive thermoelectric generator.
这是通过将放射性同位素的热能转化为电能来实现的
This works by converting heat from radioactive isotopes into electricity.
而产生的电能会为两个锂离子电池充电
This electricity charges two lithium-ion batteries,
从而允许好奇号每天执行高耗电量的任务
allowing Curiosity to carry out high power tasks each day.
RTG预计在2026年之前都能维持全功率运行
The RTG is expected to fully power Curiosity until at least 2026.
之后 功率会开始降低 好奇号的行动能力和能做的科学实验也会减少
After that, the power will decrease and the amount of movement and science it can perform.
尽管好奇号仍会继续蹒跚而行
Although Curiosity will continue to limp on,
但很有可能在电力耗尽之前 它会先“死于”机械故障或者火星的极端天气
it's entirely possible that mechanical failure
or the Martian weather might stop Curiosity's exploration before its power runs out.
火星的沙尘暴
A Martian dust storm,
可能像淹没机遇号那样 让好奇号也葬身其中
much like the one which silenced Opportunity, may also be the end of Curiosity's mission.
火星的沙尘暴可以形成云层 达到星球表面100公里高
Dust storms on Mars form clouds which can reach up to 100km above the surface of the planet.
在沙尘暴中的尘埃颗粒很小 且略带静电
The dust particles which circulate during these storms are small and slightly electrostatic,
所以它们总会粘在火星车表面 并干扰电气设备
so they can often stick to the rovers surfaces and interfere with electrical components.
好奇号也只是人类探索茫茫宇宙的探测器的一员
Curiosity is just one of many rovers which will, in time,
come to explore the endless bounds of space.
2020年夏天 毅力号火星车将启程前往火星 并在2021年初抵达
The Mars 2020 rover is set to launch later this year and is expected to land on Mars in early 2021.
当好奇号还在寻找可居住条件的时候
While Curiosity was sent to Mars to discover habitable conditions,
毅力号将会进行更伟大的任务——寻找微生物存在的真正的实锤
the 2020 mission takes things a step further – and hopes to find real proof of microbial life.
火星车变得越来越复杂 越来越智能 有用
Mars rovers are becoming more complex, more intelligent and more useful.
而尽管好奇号还有很多年的寿命
And while Curiosity may have many years left to roam,
它逐渐衰减的电力与充满威胁的沙尘暴随时都能让它彻底关机
it's electrical power weakens each day
and the threat of dust storms could easily be the end for Curiosity.
慢慢地 工程师们会逐一关闭上面的仪器设备来节省电力
Over time, engineers will slowly start shutting off instruments to preserve power,
一直到好奇号发送它最后一比特数据 并永远消失在火星
until Curiosity sends its last bit of data and disappears silently into the Martian landscape.
而无论如何 我们都不要忘记好奇号在火星收集的大量数据
Either way, we can appreciate the enormous amount of information that Curiosity has collected on Mars
与它前往那里的震撼旅程
and the incredible journey it's been on to get there.
Thanks to Brilliant for sponsoring this episode of Primal Space.
There are multiple ways to learn about a topic on the internet,
but the way Brilliant teaches you to think critically about a problem and truly understand it - is unique.
If you liked this video, you probably have an interest in things like space, science,
math and engineering - in that case Brilliant has you covered.
Brilliant is a problem solving website with a wide range of interactive courses that break complex topics down into smaller and more understandable chunks.
Brilliant isn't just about memorizing facts and formulas,
it's about developing a deep understanding of how and why things work - so you can apply them to everyday life.
To support the channel and learn more about Brilliant, visit brilliant.org/primalspace.
The first 200 people to sign up will get 20% off the yearly subscription.
Thank you very much for watching and I'll see you in the next video.